A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, International Division, Latin America and the Caribbean, Bogota and Caracas Field Office Files FA558
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, International Division, Latin America and the Caribbean, Bogota and Caracas Field Office Files
1962-1981
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA558
3 Cubic Feet 2 cubic foot boxes, 1 document box. Box 2 is legal size.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Scope and Contents
Documentation of projects, programs, meetings and consultant files.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Arrangement
Loosely alphabetical.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation maintained an office in Caracas, Venezuela from 1966 to 1972. The Foundation's Venezuela program chiefly focused on supporting initiatives and projects involved with agriculture, education, population, science and technology, and social sciences within the country. When the Foundation closed the Caracas office in 1972, it transferred responsibility for Venezuela programming to its Bogota, Colombia office.
In 1962, the Ford Foundation sent a survey team to Venezuela for the purposes of investigating if and how the Foundation could support development in the country. The Foundation established its Venezuela program based on the recommendations of this team. Initially, support for Venezuela was managed out of the Foundation's Bogota, Colombia office. Then, in 1965, the Foundation moved its Venezuela program to its Mexico City, Mexico office as part of a Mexico/Central America/Venezuela focus. The Foundation set up an independent Caracas office in 1966, and Venezuela related grants were administered by this office until its closure in 1972 (Future Status of the Venezuelan Office memo from Roy Crawley to Harry Wilhelm, September 24, 1967, Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 6262-9286 (FA739C), Report 008961). Although the Foundation reduced its funding for Venezuela projects, it continued its Venezuela program through its Bogota office (Your Colombia Visit memo from James Himes to David Bell and William Carmichael, July 3, 1973, Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 13949-17726 (FA739F), Report 015406).
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation originally maintained an office in Bogota, Colombia from 1962 to 1982. After the Bogota office's closure in 1982, responsibility for Colombia programming was administered by other Latin American country offices focusing on the Andean Region and Southern Cone until 2016 when the Foundation established another office in Bogota.
The Ford Foundation started to explore possibilities for assisting programs in Colombia in 1960 in response to requests from Colombian universities. It made its first grants to the country in 1961, and then, in 1962, it established an office in Bogota. During the time of the first Bogota office, the Foundation's Colombia program primarily focused on supporting projects and initiatives involved with education, social sciences, science and technology, agriculture, and population. Within the first 14 years of the Colombia program's existence, the Foundation had spent almost $20.6 million in grants to the country (The Ford Foundation in Colombia, 1961-1974, Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 9287-11774 (FA739D), Report 009501). At different times throughout its run, the first Bogota office was also responsible for administering the Foundation's Peru and Venezuela programs. It oversaw grants for both countries until 1965 when the Lima, Peru office was established and the Mexico City, Mexico office took over responsibility for the Venezuela program. The Bogota office resumed responsibility for the Venezuela program in 1972 after the Foundation closed its Caracas, Venezuela office.
The Ford Foundation closed the Bogota office in 1982. Regional responsibility for the Andean Region and Southern Cone was transferred to the Lima office. The Lima office administered the Foundation's Colombia program until 1991 when the Foundation then established the Andean Region and Southern Cone office in Santiago, Chile (The Ford Foundation: 40 Years in the Andean Region and Southern Cone, 2003, Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 13949-17726 (FA739F), Report 016928). The Santiago office oversaw the Foundation's support for Colombia until the Foundation opened a new Bogota office in 2016.
The current Andean Region office in Bogota oversees programming in Colombia and Peru.
- Catholic University Andres Bello -- Indiana University Cooperative Economics Project, 1967 (Box 1)
- Centro de Estudios de Desarrollo, 1964 (Box 1)
- Discretionary Project (DP) Awards, 1969-1973 (Box 1)
- Educational TV and Radio (1/2), 1962-1967 (Box 1)
- Educational TV and Radio (2/2), 1962-1967 (Box 1)
- Education Colombia II (1/2), 1967-1969 (Box 1)
- Education Colombia II (2/2), 1967-1969 (Box 1)
- FAP -- Administrative and Program Expenses -- Grant File, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
- Institute of Public Administration -- Technical Assistance to the Foundation for Community Development and Municipal Improvement -- Terminal Grant Supplement, 1966-1967 (Box 1)
- Instituto Interamericano de Fisica, 1964-1967 (Box 1)
- Local Consultancies for Trustees Visit, 1981 (Box 1)
- The Market for Ingeneros Agromimos, circa 1969 (Box 1)
- National Association of Sociology -- 7th Latin American Congress, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
- National -- Sociology -- Ackerman, Charles, 1967-1970 (Box 1)
- National -- Sociology -- General, 1967 (Box 1)
- National -- Sociology -- Latorre, Mario, 1967 (Box 1)
- National -- Sociology -- Policy Statements and Controversies, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
- National -- Sociology -- Raup, Philip, 1968 (Box 1)
- National -- Sociology -- Summary of Ford Involvement, 1968 (Box 1)
- New York/Venezuela General -- Venezuela, 1970-1977 (Box 1)
- Office of Latin America and the Caribbean (OLAC) Resource Base Activities, 1972 (Box 1)
- OFISEL -- Final Narrative Report [Spanish], 1975 (Box 1)
- Program Budget -- Correspondence IV, 1966-1968 (Box 1)
- Program Evaluations -- Venezuela, 1969 (Box 1)
- Program Related Investments, 1971 (Box 1)
- Representatives Meeting -- Kenya, 1968 (Box 1)
- Representatives Meeting -- Mexico, 1969 (Box 1)
- School of Public Administration, 1963-1965 (Box 1)
- Sociology -- Colombian Association -- Grant File (Basic Papers), 1964 (Box 1)
- CINDA Seminar Discretionary Grant Correspondence, 1974-1977 (Box 2)
- Centro Medico la Trinidad, 1971-1972 (Box 2)
- Central University of Venezuela -- Faculty of Science, 1970 (Box 2)
- Consultants -- David Fisk and David Waikart, 1980 (Box 2)
- Consultants -- Pablo Latapi, 1981 (Box 2)
- Consultants -- Lira Consultancy, 1980 (Box 2)
- Consultants -- Guillermo Briones, 1981 (Box 2)
- Consultants -- John McFadden -- Nicaragua Study, 1981 (Box 2)
- Discretionary Program Award (DPA) -- ACCION International, 1970 (Box 2)
- DP -- ASOVAC (Science Fair), 1970 (Box 2)
- DPA -- Fundacion Paternidad Responsable (Box 2)
- DPA -- Instituto de Investigacion Psicologicas`, 1972 (Box 2)
- DP -- Primer Congreso de la Association Panamerica de Sociedades de Bioquimica, 1971 (Box 2)
- IIE Fellowship Reports, 1970-1971 (Box 2)
- IVIC -- Physics, 1969 (Box 2)
- PPH -- Parents and Children Project, 1980 (Box 2)
- Regional Education DAP -- Basic Papers, 1979 (Box 2)
- Regional Education DAP -- Correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 2)
- Regional Education DAP -- ACH-PIIE Conference, 1980 (Box 2)
- Regional Education DAP -- Interamerican Seminar on Education for Justice and Human Rights, 1979 (Box 2)
- University of the Andes -- Economics Grant Supplement No. 1, 1965 (Box 3)
- University of Oriente -- School of Science -- Terminal Grant, 1967 (Box 3)
- UDO Mathematics, 1969 (Box 3)
- Venezuela -- Discretionary Project Awards, 1969 (Box 3)
- Venezuela Office -- Miscellaneous, 1969-1975 (Box 3)
- Venezuela Office -- Staff Memoranda, 1967-1970 (Box 3)
- Woodrow Wilson School -- Summer Interns -- Bowman Cutter and Howard J Howe (1/2), 1967-1969 (Box 3)
- Woodrow Wilson School -- Summer Interns -- Bowman Cutter and Howard J Howe (2/2), 1967-1969 (Box 3)
- Woodrow Wilson School -- Summer Interns -- Henry Schilling and Thomas P Storer, 1968-1969 (Box 3)